[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
it was zero percent nerves and now it's
like five percent
it just is when i let her know oh [ __ ]
just jump to five natalie are you there
oh
there you are okay cool uh so let's
begin uh
welcome to the stoa everyone
um as you can see my voice changes when
the when we're officially on record
uh i'm peter lindberg the steward of the
stoa and it still has a place for us to
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the nice edge of this very moment
so for you uh those of you who are new
here are watching for the first time
what is the stoa
no one really knows and it's probably
better to keep it that way
and no real one description does it
justice some people call it a communal
podcast some people call it a digital
campfire
we have a wisdom gym here um but i do
know that we have a lot of beautiful
outrageously sexy and highly intelligent
people
and speaking of beautiful sexy and
intelligent people
today we are very lucky to have natalie
nguyen aka
contra points an ex-philosopher and
video essayist
who does nuance and thought-provoking
videos on various cultural issues so how
today is going to work
if you're new here i'm going to warm up
natalie with a few questions if you have
any questions throw in the chat
anytime i'll call you a mute yourself
ask a question natalie
if you don't want to be on youtube just
indicate that and i'll read your
question
on your behalf so that being said i'll
give everyone
access to unmute themselves natalie
how's it going today
it is going well thank you for having me
on it's a pleasure to have you
um yeah so i thought maybe like a
question
to start off uh maybe a general one
so you started off as an ex-philosopher
on youtube
and basically became famous uh so what's
the good bad and ugly of all that
oh where do i even start with that um uh
becoming what is the good bad and ugly
of becoming
famous is it the question
that is the question uh well
the good is uh the bills are paid
that's really really the best part
honestly
is is you know you when you have neither
money nor fame which i
for most of my life hadn't either you
want
i i wanted to have both and now i
realize that only money is worth having
fame is garbage i've organized my life
all wrong i should have only thought
about money and not thought about fame
because because i love like i love like
oh
something breaks just just hire an
electrician to fix it you know
like you don't think about how much it
costs that is an immense like uh
unburdening of anxiety however fame
on the other hand is an introduction of
a lot of new anxiety that never had to
exist
and so it's like gauche to complain
it's really hard being famous but like
it is hard
actually and it like introduces a lot of
like psychological
difficulty that is like hard to imagine
until it's the situation that you're in
so for instance the
simply having like like an
unimaginable amount of people you know
tens of thousands maybe like who
are sort of building up over
years sometimes this this expectation of
you
and they think and they they sort of
build a one-sided relationship with you
and they feel that you are sort of
this important person in their lives all
the while you know nothing about these
people you know nothing about you don't
know them individually
um you know people who are hoping to get
people people feel that that you sort of
you owe them something
because they feel this closeness to you
and so they
feel um you know if you do something
that
they don't like you associate with a
person who they don't like
who they don't want to associate with
who they've felt hurt by in the past
um that feels like a personal betrayal
of a friendship to them
when to you you how could it be that you
don't know them
um but it's it's something that i've
been sort of
dealing with for a few years now and i
don't really feel like i've come much
closer to figuring out
how to live like this
yeah i like that a lot um we've been
thinking
a lot here at the store about like
parasocial relationships where people
like project on
like this avatar of you in the spectacle
um
and i'm curious like how do you
personally see
your role in this kind of conversation
culture or noise that's happening
and what do you think is being projected
on you from kind of all the different
tribes
well i think um you know it's something
that's really
changed also over the last few years
like it's that's the other strange thing
about like my
you know youtube journey in particular
is that i've kind of been
a person very much like uh
in i mean in transition obviously but
also like
i've been like i feel like three
different people now in the last few
years
and it's
it you know so just based on what i'm
putting out it's kind of
weird to feel like i am represented
by these this whole
like sequence of you know videos that
i've created or these
these moments that i've put online
because the way people perceive you on
the internet is
the past is is just as present as it
always was
and the um you know you don't they don't
perceive
people don't perceive online you know so
when you look at like someone's youtube
channel what you're looking at is a grid
of videos
and you can just click on any of them
and and there's an immediacy to video
right because you're seeing a person's
face they're talking to you're hearing a
voice
um it seems like a present but to me you
know those old very i mean
absolutely unwatchable to me are videos
that are two years old even
even one year old sometimes and like
but it's odd to me that to other people
they're still finding these videos for
the first time
and getting to know this version of me
that i've
long moved past um
as far as who that person is well sure
you have all different factions and that
you know
i mean different things too like to some
people and they're like
inspiration to be a gender transition
you know to other people i am
the person who like talked them out of
their right-wing beliefs
to other people i am this like super
villain who
is like grifting everyone and is just
like
breaking in money by by exploiting
people's
desire to have you know
to i don't know hear about leftist
politics or something
and so yeah you have a lot of things
projected on to you
a bit from hero to villain to you know
everything in between right yeah and i
can imagine like um
there's like egoic highs and kind of
like having to do jiu-jitsu and
narcissism and stuff like that 100
and i'm curious how do you have any
personal techniques for that and maybe
how does your like philosophical
background
inform you in those techniques or with
those techniques
uh the comedian chris fleming has his
phrase uh the self-esteem
tower of terror where you know you'll go
from
believing that you are a queer icon
you know here to bring bring relief to
the to the poor masses just to thinking
that you are the scum of the earth
i mean i sort of i don't know i don't
really feel that i'm either of those
things
i i guess i there's sort of been moments
when i was like sort of my channel was
growing
where there was a kind of feeling of
like ascendancy destiny for greatness
like
this kind of delusional high i guess but
i'm sort of
immune to that now like i don't feel
that i have the highs
anymore um to some extent i do still
have the lows though
so i think that
i don't know it becomes like i don't
know why it is it's a kind of negativity
bias and like
in terms of like what becomes like
emotionally prominent like
i find that oh people people like
people like wanting to kiss your feet
and worshiping you like
that it's a remarkable how fast that
becomes this kind of like
white noise but somehow people despising
you always
staying fresh
i don't know why that is but i would say
that to me the the struggle has been
more not to be dragged down by the
negativity than it has
to to have to worry about being
delusionally over inflated
um and there was maybe a couple times
that i feel like it got delusionally
over inflated along the way
um but i feel like at least for the last
year the other has not
i haven't really it's not been the
problem let's put it that way
i promise this is not the bait and
switch uh to turn this into a therapy
session
but if you have a sofa ready you know i
might wanna um so
uh i will turn to the q a and i'll try
to
kind of pick a question that's like uh
with the same
energy but it might be all over the
place you might get questions kind of
from every angle but i think uh hannah
has a really good
question that would follow up on that so
hannah if you can unmute yourself and
ask your question
that was a while ago let me just scroll
up if you please
i can copy and paste it for you that
would be amazing
boom and hannah's a super fan girl uh
natalie by the way she's just like
no i don't tell her she was like peter
oh my god
[Laughter]
oh i'm blushing yep
so i get the sense that you draw on your
own inner world your
thoughts your emotions your psychology
in a lot of your videos and i'm
wondering how do you get to know those
parts of yourself so well
when a lot of those parts are the ones
that
many of us don't want to admit are even
part of us to begin with so if you're
okay speaking to that i'm very curious
well it's um i find that it's actually
somehow easier sometimes to blurt out
my secrets to a million people
than it would be to have a one-on-one
conversation with someone i know well
about it
um i think it's because something about
the media is
this technology it sort of provides
um this kind of illusion of intimacy an
illusion of privacy
where uh i mean i guess i'm sort of more
used to this now but i feel like when i
when i first started talking about very
personal things on youtube
i would often have this moment like i
had i'd written the video i'd recorded
the video i'd edited the video
and then i finally published it and i'm
watching it for the first time
in the youtube window with the likes and
dislikes and the comments under it and
i'm like
and there's off it was often a moment of
panic like oh god like people can see
this like
this is not just my private video diary
which somehow
like when i'm working on it it often
feels like it is like
there's a loneliness in the process of
making these videos
where you know i'm often i don't know i
have weird work habits i'm working at
night
i'm when you're speaking into a camera
alone at night in a room by yourself
it this is somehow easy to kind of
like get into this mindset of like
intimately divulging like these things
that are going on in your life
and then you know well
then you edit it together and you and
you turn it into entertainment somehow
and
and then only once you've published it
doesn't really
hit you what you've done and uh yeah i
i i don't know how to how do i get in
touch with these things well
it becomes i don't know at a certain
point the feedback starts to enter into
you know because you have to listen to a
lot of commentary about yourself when
you're putting yourself
out there so you know there's 15 000
comments like
i have a tendency to read a lot of them
and then that kind of
often sometimes it's a challenge to me
and then i'll think about that and
then i'll have a longing to further
explain myself
which uh sometimes is the motivation
um yeah i
i don't know i used to i used to be a
great like keeper of like
i used to have like a diary that i wrote
for 16 years that i wrote
like almost every day and i actually
just recently uh
shredded all of it it was this
like big like 38 gallon trash bag
completely full
of shredded diary that was very
satisfying to throw away
but yeah i don't have a private journal
anymore it's so it's just
uh just all blurted into the microphone
and did you have a follow-up question
if i could sneak in a follow-up comment
i would like to say on the subject that
cringe video in particular helped me see
a lot of things myself that i hadn't
seen before
and i feel grateful to you for that oh
well i'm glad you found it helpful
i i found it helpful too actually i feel
like that video more than any other one
i made
was a kind of um it was like a purge for
me
like i felt like this this ugly thing
that i've been sort of tormenting me for
a few years
like to just go to just to analyze it
and to like
cage it you know they put it on display
kind of like
it was a huge relief to me and honestly
i feel like making that video has
has kind of has really changed my
thinking sense so i'm glad it
was also helpful to a viewer
all right uh julia you had a question if
you can unmute yourself
julia moore are you there
all right i am a huge fan um
just by the way i love how authentic you
are
in all of your videos um my question is
you started creating content to critique
the right but your latest video centered
largely in questioning the far left how
do you feel about that shift
well i think um it's something that i do
i i am reflective about i think that
the reason for it has to do with the
shift in
the people around me so when i started
out on youtube
like youtube was it was like i mean it
was like a borderline like nazi
recruitment grounds like
it was so far right so predominantly
that like i guess part of part of the
motivation for me early on
was being like like in the first few
videos i made they got like
just down voted like overwhelmingly down
voted because
i was you know that the arguments i was
making were things like
maybe feminism isn't going to destroy
western civilization you know
maybe black lives matter is not a
terrorist organization like
like you know hell bent on cucking the
white male or whatever these people were
saying
and like i guess i
uh youtube has changed it's really
really changed since then
and i guess i i i
you know as as long ago as 2017 i was
making videos that kind of dealt with
like
the the far left like this character
tabby who i've kind of always used as
this the mascot of that position
i mean why was why did i create tabby
well because there's a lot of tabbies
in my i was seeing them all over the
place on twitter and my mentions
it became sort of unavoidable um
and i do i mean i i do feel it's
somewhat worth talking about like it's
worth addressing these people and it's
worth addressing
but to me that like that this represents
like
a problem with the left like a
self-defeating
self-destructive tendency that i do
think genuinely does need to be
critiqued
but i'm also aware that i do have like
at this point like
a borderline pathological fixation on it
and
that's partially because i'm like like
the amount of the amount of like a
vitriol i
already got online is so this like these
days it's so disproportionately from
that
kind of person like i don't the the
right wing harassment is is
nothing compared to the amount of like
of of kind of hatred and negativity
coming at me from that
part of the internet that i think i kind
of dwell on it
but i also i have to remind myself these
these are not people with a real power
in the world
and so i do know that like i know on
some level that i'm
too obsessed with this but uh it's also
hard to ignore
the thing that's constantly screaming at
you
yeah i totally agreed with your last
video thank you so much for answering my
question
you're very welcome thank you cool
um kevin you are up i will copy and
paste your question
in the chat
hello miss points it's a pleasure to be
able to speak with you
um so you've played many different
characters and you've represented
a variety of perspectives from these
different meta tribes
you just mentioned tabby the anarchist
cat girl and
you've you know spoken about incels and
centrist libs and
all right youtubers um i'm wondering if
you have any like rituals or techniques
or i mean you might have spoken about
this a little bit like
for example like when you get all these
cat girl comments right and you're going
to play tabby or whatever
how do you like embody this character
that you're going to represent
or do you have any ways that you like
get better into their perspective when
you're about to go on camera
and um be them and be their sort of
mouthpiece in the video i guess well
there's the writing
side of it and then there's the like
perfecting performance side of it
and i suppose that for also i suppose
that the costuming side of it
but for the writing side of it often
what i will do is simply spend
some time like really studying
the um like the the the
text that like the actual way these
people will speak whoever it is
if i make a turf character or a a cat
girl character or
you know whatever it is like because
often i find that there's um
if you can if you sort of if you don't
look at the way that they actually
will write actually it will speak like
you're going to create something that's
less
vibrant and lively i find than if you
sort of source it from
the original uh you know the real world
material so
like for this last video i you know i
had tweeted a bunch of stuff already
encouraging people to vote in this
election and like a bunch of people had
retweeted those
you know calling me a lib and saying
like you know
all this kind of stuff and so i went and
i looked at those tweets and i just like
picked up um some phrases
from those tweets like like the
electoral farce
like that was a phrase that someone had
used on twitter like i was like oh
that's good put that in put that in
um or like oh what was it uh like
uh t thought
normie like normie i forgot what it is
typical
he thought normie live like something
like like you can't just make this up
you have to go out you have to go into
the field
and and find it um and then as far as
like
i guess the costuming is very kind of
caricature based
uh you know like the the the emojis i
guess
of a leftist twitter handle like i'll
just grab all of them i can find and
shove them into one thing and some of
them i just have them as pins like
some people criticize the costing of
tabby to say
well why does she have a hammer and
sickle and a rose
and uh you know a black flag like these
are these are contradictory leftist
symbols i'm like but they have those
those people have on twitter
unfarlow twitter that's what people put
in their accounts they use all those
emojis and so uh
you know i get it from that and then as
for like the the way i
act a character that's often just
totally made up
right like i think that i try to pull
out of some part of myself
like the way tabby talks i mean i guess
tommy's just cute right because she's a
cat girl cowgirl's cute
and then also like some of it's just
accidental like
those fangs they give i have like i get
a particular kind of like list
when i have the fangs then and so i i
don't know if i can imitate it without
the fangs of a tabby
tabby she has like a kind of it's a this
is this is like
distinctive like vampire fang lisp that
she has it's also extremely cute
and then the character is just
kind of i don't know a combination of
all these aspects of fields
i hope it feels like at the same time
like real and also very like
you know larger than life
any follow up kevin um
no no no thank you for your response
you're welcome
all right uh uh we got our troublemaker
bonita roy up next
yes my dogs are barking um
natalie oh man i love your stuff
it's it works on me on a level that like
i'm still processing um my questions
um a little difficult
um so i'll
i'll give you i'm gonna frame it in the
background like i grew up i love cher
i mean i'm not i'm kind of older okay so
and i love shara and i love the whole
performative thing she does and
and the same with you i mean the way you
the way you
produce your stuff and the creativity
that goes into it this is a big
attraction for me
you know the the amount of effort um
the kitsch and the seriousness and all
this stuff is
is delightful and
and it's not surface i mean this is like
a trick
right to do that much performance and
and then yet it's not surface
when cher got older she she did this
interview for i think vogue or something
and she told a story of um
chaz at the time um they were walking
through a store or something
and chaz said to her ma
can you just stop being cher
and cher said i got it but i didn't have
anything to put in its place
and so like my question for you
is like is there a place that you settle
like um and it
you know or is that still in process for
you
um and and and if you want to like
my other part of the question to like
draw it out not about you
um is i'm also fascinated with this
youtube
uh persona self
and she's a lot younger she's doing a
completely different thing but the
my question is like uh what
what like how do you relate to the
internet
and the personas and this new thing
that's shaping you
shaping really young people like so i
don't know this is a
big question but i know you have a
really uh
a really robust uh intellect also
so somehow that's my question and
hopefully that
that's a fun question for you yeah so i
think
that
presenting a series of different
personas on youtube
is actually in some ways like a
violation of what the fundamental
idea of being a youtuber is supposed to
be because i know for a lot of people
like
the original attraction of youtube is
authenticity
is that you can kind of relate to this
person
who's just sitting on their bed and you
know
if it feels like someone you know right
that's the the parasocial
thing right on youtube is especially
strong in part because
it seems like a real a very real person
right unlike
you know people you see on tv or you
know share
um and i think that
that's always kind of been an illusion
like i mean sometimes it's literally
like
i mean this goes all the way back to
like 2007
2006 maybe like i think one of the first
youtubers was like
lonely girl 15 who like people related
to her and her
like little drama that she had the high
school story lines
turns out this was a scripted show that
was not presenting itself
as that originally um i mean i think
that
i obviously people do
view me as authentic in some way like
people's you know because i do talk
about like very personal
things but i do it in a very kind of
stylized um uh sort of
i guess my my style of presentation
doesn't scream authenticity the way that
most i guess more traditional youtubers
do
right i'm not sitting on my bed and just
being like hey guys i just need to get
this off my chest
like here's what's going on like no like
like cameras like like the
the video starts and it's like a set
there's lights
i mean i'm obviously have spent time
getting ready to film the video and i'm
not just like
impromptu like divulging my what's on my
mind
right so and there's a script so so
that's that's
even another level of like planning i
suppose but
i don't know i think that to me but
to me it feels more honest i suppose to
present
that way considering that like i am
putting a lot of thought into this
there is a lot of planning if i were to
present as if
i was just like you know sitting on my
bed speaking what's on my mind
i think that you know that would be that
would be more of an illusion in a way
than you know this ridiculous can't be
like cast of characters
um now as far as like
why like with the effect it has on me
like why i'm doing it uh
well i think part of it is it's fun you
know i like it
like the same reason that i guess you
like to watch it it's fun
like uh i mean it also like if i want to
if i were to like psychoanalyze it more
i suppose like i've been i don't know
the last few years i've been making this
channel has been a very like
some sort of like pseudo you know second
adolescent
time in my life in a way and you know
when you're going through
a period like that like you're you're
sort of i'm sort of finding out who you
are
and the way you do that is you try out
some different
options and personas and see if any of
them if any of them takes
and so i know i've been doing that like
i think there's a lot of like
inconsistency with like what is the
persona exactly that i'm presenting on
this channel it's really changed over
the last few years
um and i think i maybe sort of have
gotten away with that a little more
because of the cut over costumed over
produced like nature of the show
and the fact that i also am like doing
these like literally fictional
characters
so uh i guess it's it also you know
maybe gives me a little bit of distance
like um
you know these like debate videos often
when i do those like
debate videos i have like ideas or
arguments that like
i don't necessarily i'm not necessarily
sure
i agree with them or not but i just want
to try them out and see where they go
and so i'll make a character have the
argument instead of me
and then they can argue with another
character and then you know
see where that leads like i guess that's
kind of the fun of writing fiction right
sometimes
you think because you're thinking
instead of just thinking like you think
we're reading i don't know academic
writing or philosophy paper where you're
just thinking
what do i think what makes sense like
what is logical you're thinking
how does this character feel how would
this character respond
to that argument and that's a fun way to
to write
i think because sometimes when i'm
writing
i'll get some i'll get surprised by what
comes out
on the page like because i'm not because
because i'm thinking through
what characters thought and then
sometimes the character
will have a thought that i wouldn't
necessarily have had
that's kind of that's i don't know that
can be productive in a way too
do you have a quick follow-up penita no
i just that's a wonderful uh response
and
yeah the process is is certainly
um yeah remarkable
and and and i'm sure there's so much
more you can share about what it takes
and
um yeah the content and the performance
the creativity is extraordinary yeah
thank you so much
um natalie we're eight minutes to the
hour
um do you have any uh additional time
like uh
we're only scheduled to seven i'm
joining you very late too so so
feel free to go 20 minutes over whatever
cool cool that works
well um katie uh
you are up
katie kelly yes i'm here can you guys
yep okay yep great hey natalie um
i was wondering if you could speak to
how you select the topics that you
choose to cover in your videos and why
like you mentioned before that it's
almost a process like a personal journal
that you upload and then shoot out
into the internet and like to pretend is
anonymous like
are you just talking about what's most
present to you in the moment
or with the level of influence and
subscriber count that you have do you
feel like a responsibility to cover
certain topics
or not talk about certain topics i was
wondering if fear of
censorship also might play into certain
topics that you choose to cover or not
and
you could just talk about that a little
bit yeah i would say that it's a variety
of motive
a variety of factors all can sort of
consider when
choosing topics one is simply like what
am i thinking about a lot lately like
what do i like
when i'm taking a shower or making
breakfast or whatever
like what won't stop popping into my
head that's kind of
the most i guess natural the most like
authentic if you will like way of
choosing a topic
um but it's it's only one of like other
a few
considerations i also consider like does
anyone want to watch a video about this
like is this you know is this something
that
people care about or is it relevant um i
will think about
um is this
important like like is you know like
like so voting
but i didn't know this was not a video
that came from my soul
you know like i wasn't like oh i can't
i'm so excited to talk about voting for
joe biden like like no i don't care well
i mean i do care but like
but i i made the video because i thought
it was important
i felt like um um i guess compelled to
use my platform to do something about
this election
and that's what i did because so that
was more like that's more like
i want to say something about this
because i want to have an effect
on this particular issue more so than
like i need to express my feelings
i don't really need to express my
feelings about joe biden as it turns out
but i do want people to vote trump out
so that's why i made that video
um then sometimes
um i'm trying to think of every time a
video that's just like
yeah this will get views like
occasionally i guess
i'll do it like well it is it's sort of
it's a combination i mean it's never
just to get views but i think i did
originally
start researching jordan peterson
because i was like what does it do with
this guy
like everyone is talking about this like
maybe i should look into this
like this would be a good video um you
know people love a feud
um so i started like listening to jordan
peterson's podcast
and but then i was like oh i i really
want to make a video about this now
because once i started listen like you
know getting into it then
i was like i feel like i have a lot to
say about this so
i uh i in that case you know
i was initially motivated to explore the
topic by like
you know what's popular what's what's
getting views what do people want to
hear about
but i think if i had looked into jordan
peters and found like oh i have nothing
to say about this i wouldn't have made a
video
so it's it's a combination of things
yeah
cool thanks can i do a follow-up quick
is there any topic that like maybe you
would want to do that you feel
like limited from doing for some reason
or another
yeah i definitely have i do sometimes
think of topics
where it's like oh i care a lot about
this but i don't think anyone
really needs to hear from me about this
um like i don't know
i sometimes have ideas but like art in
particular or activities about
music or about i don't know a movie i
liked or something but the thing
there's a couple of reasons i don't do
that i don't know maybe someday i will
but one is like
this is not really what my channel is
about oftentimes it's a
topic that would have like less interest
um i would think from viewers and then
also
you know especially when it comes to
like movies there's already such a
gigantic
like group of creators doing this that i
feel like
do we really need another film youtuber
like i'm better off doing my own thing
thank you so there's some uh people uh
teasing me in the chat and actually
privately messaging me to ask you this
question
so full disclosure jordan peterson was
actually my therapist for two years
before he entered into the culture war
um and i recently wrote about him in my
journals
one entry called rescuing the father and
so mike
my question my question for you
is do you think jordan peterson could be
redeemed on the left
and if so what would have to happen and
maybe what would he have to do
i think he could be um i i feel for
me it would help to have
some kind of apology clarification on
his
views about trans people because this is
really what uh what it got me
not that i think i don't think he's a
raging transphobe but
i do think that one of the reasons i got
interested in this
person in the first place this is a man
who got famous
for sounding the alarm that
free speech was ending in canada because
you know pronoun jail was coming
the pronoun you know secret police were
going to be knocking on doors at any
moment
and like something needed to be said
well i mean
in 2017 i or i remember like
one of the most frequent of arguments i
would i would get
you know this i did a uh i did a like a
live event in vancouver and someone
grilled me for 20 minutes about this you
know
why aren't trans people doing more to
speak out about the end of free speech
that we're demanding
you know and this is all came here
jordan peterson well
it was all complete exaggeration
like not a single person has gone to
canada for program and pronoun misuse
since bill c-16 was passed um
and i think that this was a completely
alarmist
um non-issue that
that's main effect was to like you know
give get another pretext for people to
be for to dislike and distrust
trans people and so to me that's that's
the big that's that's
that is the worst grudge i have against
against dr peterson
um i would like to hear him address bill
c-16 again and maybe
engage with whether that whether it was
really necessary to
to generate that controversy in the
first place
um you know i'm less concerned about all
this talk about post-modern neo-marxism
which
i think doesn't make any sense but
that's okay you're allowed to not make
sense
natalie wynn and jordy peterson at the
store
i want the in conversation
sorry i missed that party
um all right so
i hope we're still friends natalie um
even though we're not we weren't really
friends before but i hope you can still
potentially be friends against you
uh nathan you are up
did you guys see me you hear me
hello hey uh big fan natalie um thanks
for
doing this peter this is a a real treat
to to listen to
i guess i wanted to ask something that
natalie i know you've addressed sort of
in the past but
i'm wondering at this point in time how
important
do you think debate and conversation
with people on like the center to the
right wing
is for uh left-wing figures just given
the sort of
institutional divide and i know um
there was that uh new york times piece
that you were kind of featured in with
that kid
caleb kane over the kind of the
alt-right rabbit hole
and how he kind of stumbled upon you and
then other creators like
destiny the streamer who does these
types of debates
but anyway i'm just i guess curious to
to get your thoughts on
how important the uh how you find the
utility of that like is it something
worth doing is it something you think
more creators should be doing
um or is it kind of all just theatrics
in your mind at this point
well you're asking how important is it
to have conversations with centrists
with conservatives
i suppose it depends what you mean by
conversations
um i think that you know this through
okay there's kind of three things that
we could mean
one is you know talking one-on-one with
these people as you run across them in
your life another is
you know a produced public debate event
or just or you know discussion event
discussion podcast discussion on
on a panel whatever it might be
and then the third is a kind of
simulated conversation
with a person who's not present like
which is what my videos are right
because my video i don't have i don't
bring centrists or conservatives onto my
channel and
uh you know have a conversation
with them what i do instead is i produce
a piece of media
a video essay that is directed at an
audience whether that includes
these people who i know people who
disagree are going to watch
and to some extent i'm thinking of to a
large extent i suppose
i'm thinking of imagining an audience
that sort of is going to disagree with
me about things
as i'm writing so
i think that now no one has an
obligation of course to have
conversations with
with people who uh you know have very
different views particularly since those
conversations can often become like
can touch on issues that are very
personal so i understand that they want
do you desire to avoid it
um but i also think that it is
is extremely useful and important um
for the people who are up to doing that
and who can do it effectively
so i don't know i don't know i'm not
really a great debater
um i guess i have some lingering
resentment that i was never allowed to
become a great debater because
people people hated it so much when i
used to do that but uh
but you know you have like like destiny
like i think that what he does is is
very very useful
um and i'm i'm glad that
there's people like that who do do what
they do um you know who actually do have
these conversations
um and i also i mean i hope and i think
that what i do is
as useful in my own way even though i'm
not having these direct like
confrontations
like i think that if i were to produce
you know as some people some people say
this is a criticism of me like
oh she produces she just produces
content for centrist normies
like she doesn't even make content for
leftists it's like well yeah
like i i mean there's not that many
leftists and like
why what do i need to convince them of
anyway um
i don't know i i guess i'm increasingly
aware that about
you know a lot of people watching me are
leftists and so there's
there's i know that that's you know part
of my audience and so my stuff
it does is for them um but
to me like especially if i'm talking
about i don't know
um well
like the pleas for trans acceptance is
the most obvious one like i don't know
most people in this world
don't understand trans people they're
not very sympathetic
um so to me like all the utility of a
video like that
is to try to like make make the case
to people who um
you know who are already on board to see
if you can pull more people on board
because that's that's making myself
useful i think i think much more so
than making like i don't know i don't
know what the alternative here is like
entertain like safe space entertainment
like i don't know i don't see i i really
don't see that as being as valuable as
well i'm sure that it is valuable
actually
but but it's not really my what i sort
of feel called to do
um what i feel called to do is to kind
of pull in
uh to sort of be a magnet i suppose for
people not
otherwise likely to care
or to um you know become
interested in these kinds of topics yeah
it's great thanks so much really
appreciate it
right so someone sent this question to
me privately um
do you still read philosophy and if so
what do you read
it's been a long while since i really
read philosophy
i uh well sometimes like you know
go go read it read an article on the
stand for encyclopedia philosophy just
to refresh my memory about a topic
i haven't done a very heavy philosophy
reading
in a while though for a video i'm making
later this year i'm going to read
i'm going to reread nietzsche's
genealogy of morals cover to cover
because it's irrelevant
but but so sometimes i'll do something
like that i don't know
what was the last time i was i was
really reading philosophy i'm trying to
think
um well i read um
i read some like anarchist and marxist
theory i guess a couple years ago
because
that was becoming um it was becoming
popular and i wanted to be you know
to have read it so i could keep up with
with the children
you know i've read um you know the
conquest of bread which
i had never uh i never that's not it's
not at the top much in academic
philosophy so i read
i read that i i read that so i know what
bread tube is
um i uh
have i read anything else not really
i i i find that those kind
i don't know at some point i think i was
i mean maybe maybe i'm close to that
point
i will start to miss those kind of deep
dives into difficult works because i
think there is some utility and reading
stuff like that it's like
i don't know it trains your brain to
like
focus on one thing for a while and
it's the opposite of what youtube will
tend to do
so i guess but for the most part no i
don't read much philosophy these days i
think that
being a grad student you know phd
student in philosophy in my mid-20s
was it was kind of enough of that for a
while
like i said i feel like i look back on
those years of my life and i see
like years you know maybe not lost but
years i spent with my face in a book
and like i guess i sort of
want to do other things now but um
yeah i'm sure i should all come crawling
back at some point
is there any like uh thinker or
intellectual maybe uh
um not necessarily in philosophy that is
resonating with you lately
lately um i got i guess i
well nietzsche and uh martin luther king
i guess i think i think well i think
martin luther king is something of a
philosopher
i think that especially i think about
power and love
and like this kind this kind of
discourse which
where king explicitly references
nietzsche actually
and this sort of um
i guess because i think it's kind of a
central question
and anyone who's working on justice is
um you know the relationship between
like the kind of christian
conception of love uh and
the fact that politics
is about power um so i
don't know this is this is the question
that's been sort of interesting to me
lately i've been reading
uh you know as i said martin luther
king's
speeches and uh nietzsche's
genealogy of morals
awesome so uh we have about 10 minutes
left
um jeremy johnson you are
next
great so hello natalie uh love your
videos
um my question was it was going to be
about the role
of content creation as a leftist as a
media creator
um in the context of pedagogy in terms
of
education um pivoting let's say popular
culture
towards leftist ideas in general
consciousness raising so just sort of
how you see
your role in doing that and performing
that and how entertainment can also be
education
um sorry could you just just
say the question part one more time sure
uh
just how you see your role as not only
an entertainer but also
an educator in the sense that education
can also be entertaining
right and so being on the left
and creating popular content but also
doing education at the same time into
sort of the role for that
in media today i suppose i don't
i i saw myself as much more educational
early on where i would do these like i
would do a video about systemic racism
and it would be
it would draw a lot on you know research
and then i would try to make it somewhat
entertaining as i went now i guess
the video the videos i do lately are
sort of
uh they're more like argumentative i
suppose and educational
but oftentimes there is like an
educational element that comes along the
way
there's often like moments or a section
of a video
that is kind of like a lecture
um like you know in the i'm thinking
about justice part one
that was kind of an educational video
like i had um
you know when you have screens coming up
showing you know retributive justice and
and you know whatever other kinds of
justice i'm analyzing like
it is education folded into the
entertainment i guess i see what i'm
doing as
um
i guess it would be more like directly
pedagogical if the channel was like oh
like here's an overview of topics and
philosophy which like
i'm going to make entertaining which
i've actually thought about doing that
like i've thought about doing a series
that is more um
uh more like that you know what i mean
like i guess
i um
i've preferred instead though to i don't
know
maybe some maybe that will be kind of my
like post contour points project
is to do something like that but for the
time being i guess i'm
i guess what interests me more is is
addressing these like very like sort of
current topics
and then sort of folding in some
pedagogical elements
using like uh you know the current event
or whatever
i'm talking about uh as the framing
device and then
you know while i'm at it oh you can talk
about different different theories of
justice
or oh we can talk about you know the
psychology of um
uh you know secondhand embarrassment
right or
or whatever it is that the topic is
any follow-up uh jeremy
uh no that was great that was great i
think um
well maybe this uh do you see this as a
good strategy or an effective strategy
that other content creators
could take up just in terms of you know
i don't know i don't know what the
percentage would be 70 current events 30
oh by the way that's sort of this idea
or this concept
in terms of making these things
accessible
yeah i think absolutely i mean people
have been doing this you know there's
always been
people who've been making sort of
edutainment
i guess some of it is like maybe a
little bit less deranged and
stuff i make like i'm thinking about
like carl sagan or um
uh that's that's sort of television and
education at once and
i uh does anyone do comedy
in education oh i'm sure people do i'm
just not thinking of it
but yeah it's becoming a pretty common
genre on youtube
absolutely
all right um so someone named jp has a
question
uh and it would be quite surprised that
this turns out to be jordan peterson so
uh
jp if you could unmute yourself
it's not jordan pearson but um next time
yeah
yeah i had a i had a quick question
just um i i i'm not as familiar i guess
with your backstory
um so i i just
that i guess you had your parents were
psych
psychologists i guess and i just wanted
to know
how how they kind of impacted your
your thinking as a thinker as a youtuber
um you know and just if you know your
your thoughts on your thoughts on that
like how you may have
adopted some of their thoughts or had
deviations
with some of your your thoughts about
certain subjects
um with your parents well growing up
you i mean there's conversations that
are had
with parents and so it's inevitable that
you are influenced by
their ideas my mom was uh
my mom is a doctor who was involved with
communists in the 70s and we've had i've
had many conversations with her
about um you know
radical left swing thinking and activism
and like
the viability of it and how you need to
balance that against the need
to like make a place for yourself and
the world and find happiness in the
world
which is something that she has always
kind of tried to tell me
that like you cannot she always says
told me you can't put your happiness on
whole until
the communist revolution because if i
had done that in the 70s i'd be very
unhappy now
you know and
my dad is an emotions researcher um
i i would not i have not really for the
most part
talked to him about these these videos
but i will say that when i was working
on cringe
um i mean he's he's
edited an anthology on emotions that
includes a whole
section on secondhand embarrassment and
i did ask him for
reading recommendations
sure and and and what what about
religiously speaking or
are you um like protestant catholic
jewish
well i was raised of going to a
protestant church um which i rejected
when i was about 15.
yeah all right thanks for
answering my question you're welcome
so i think uh be good to end here
because we have another event coming at
the bottom of the hour
uh natalie any kind of closing thoughts
for us uh anything that came alive for
you that was alien
oh um
i feel that i feel like i've made myself
clear i guess i uh
thank you guys for having me on i'm
sorry that i was late
no worries uh late natalie is better
than no natalie as
we'd like to say here at the stoa um so
i'll make some
closing announcements in a moment but
natalie thanks so much for coming to
stowa today uh that was a lot of fun
love to have you um back and to
plug uh a couple events uh we have one
in 10 minutes with daniel
schmuckenberger this is his last session
on the sons maker in residence series
you can rcp on the website we have noam
chomsky coming in on november 16th
at 5 30 pm eastern time you can rsvp
there
let's see what else uh events i should
plug maybe do you want to plug
settler sexualities that's coming up on
november 6th
yeah absolutely thanks peter i'm going
to be hosting that conversation with kim
talbear
and it'll be discussing a lot about the
way that
our family structures are an imposition
from
the colonial uh history that that
affects north america and i think it's
going to be
really really cool it's going to touch
on a lot of really hot button topics and
i definitely recommend hanging out and
asking her your questions
because she's just a really robust
amazing uh intellect for sure
beautiful and i'm gonna let's see if i
can give my tech issue i want to plug
this event
so it has the videos on uh
i'm gonna share my screen boom
it is maybe not the end of the world
election party all-day 24-hour election
party we've got existential
dance party we've got socratic speed
dating um
shame breakthrough boot camp stoic
breath a lot of cool stuff
so that's on november 3rd it's going to
be the website tonight
check that out here is our website
patreon and stop stack if you would like
to check those out
again natalie everyone thank you for
coming to stowa today
and i will stop here and then play some